<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A brief narration of the plotting, beginning &amp; carrying on of that execrable rebellion and butcherie in Ireland. With the unheard of devilish-cruelties and massacres by the Irish-rebels, exercised upon the Protestants and English there. Faithfully collected out of depositions, taken by commissioners under the Great Seal of Ireland. Hereunto are added observations, discovering the actions of the late King; and manifesting the concernment of the Protestant-army now imployed in Ireland. Published by special authority.</title>
            <author>Waring, Thomas, 17th cent.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1650</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 103 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 36 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A97166</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing W873</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E596_2</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R204016</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99863748</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99863748</idno>
            <idno type="VID">165575</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A97166)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 165575)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 91:E596[2])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A brief narration of the plotting, beginning &amp; carrying on of that execrable rebellion and butcherie in Ireland. With the unheard of devilish-cruelties and massacres by the Irish-rebels, exercised upon the Protestants and English there. Faithfully collected out of depositions, taken by commissioners under the Great Seal of Ireland. Hereunto are added observations, discovering the actions of the late King; and manifesting the concernment of the Protestant-army now imployed in Ireland. Published by special authority.</title>
                  <author>Waring, Thomas, 17th cent.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[8], 32, 25-30, [2], 41-64 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by B. Alsop and T. Dunster. And are to be delivered at Bernard Alsop's house in Grub-street,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>MDCL. [1650]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Attributed to Thomas Waring.</note>
                  <note>Title page in red and black.</note>
                  <note>The first leaf is blank.</note>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "Mar. 19. 1649"; the L in imprint date crossed out.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Ireland --  History --  Rebellion of 1641 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-02</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-02</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-03</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-03</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:165575:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A Brief NARRATION OF THE Plotting, Beginning &amp; Carrying on of that Execrable REBELLION and BUTCHERIE <hi>IN</hi> IRELAND.</p>
            <p>With the unheard of Deviliſh-Cruelties and Maſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cres by the <hi>Iriſh-Rebels,</hi> exerciſed upon the PROTESTANTS and <hi>Engliſh</hi> there.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Faithfully Collected out of</hi> Depoſitions, <hi>taken by Commiſſioners under the Great Seal of IRELAND.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Hereunto are added OBSERVATIONS, Diſcovering the Actions of the late KING; and manifeſting the Concernment of the PROTESTANT-Army now imploy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in <hi>IRELAND.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Publiſhed by ſpecial Authority.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed by <hi>B. Alſop</hi> and <hi>T. Dunſter.</hi> And are to be delivered at <hi>Bernard Alſop</hi>'s houſe in Grub-ſtreet. MDCL.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="preface">
            <pb facs="tcp:165575:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:165575:2"/>
            <head>The Preface.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He execrable Butchery exerciſed by the <hi>Iriſh,</hi> in eight years laſt past, up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the Engliſh Proteſtants, hath ſo fil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led all good hearts with ſorrow and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtation, that it is impoſſible to repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent it with greater, and more ſolemn Agravati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, than the bare recital, Now as it was an action ſo fouly criminal in all, both divine and humane conſiderations; ſo hath there not any complied with the Instruments of it, or afforded them the least favour, that have not either found their ruine, or may not (if their eyes be open) ſee, they are a haſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing towards it. Whereas thoſe (I means the Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of <hi>England</hi>) that ever declared their deteſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of it; and did ever effectually proſecute a Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venge, (even in the middeſt of their danger, and cruel oppoſitions of the prevaricating Engliſh Court) have found the hand of God ſo mightily and viſibly aſſisting them, that they have triumphed over their Opreſsors, and ſeen all their own endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vours
<pb facs="tcp:165575:3"/>crowned with ſucceſſe. Now as the comfort they have reapt by their integrity, is not ſmall; ſo (no doubt) will they find it enlarged, when they have found, that all men are ſatisfied, both with the justneſſe of their proceeding, and amazed with the horror of ſuch exquiſite wickedneſs: Which that it may be known; not onely to this Age, but to the Children that are yet to be born; it is held fit, that ſuch diſcoveries as have been brought to them, ſhould clearly and freely be brought to light; and laid open, that all men might bear witneſs againſt thoſe Savages, againſt whom the bloud of ſo many innocents cries behind the Altar.</p>
            <p>To this end, there is publiſhing a large volume of <hi>Depoſitions</hi> (though far ſhort of what might have been produced, a great part of that Iſland being ever ſince in the hands of the Rebels) where the Reader may at large ſatisfie himſelf of all the cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumſtances which may ſtile the Maſsacre Horrid and Diabolical. But becauſe that volume is ſwoln to a great largeneſs, and therefore cannot readily expect to paſs the Preſs, it hath been thought fit in the mean time, to publiſh this ſmall Tract, as an Introduction, or fore-runner (or call it what you pleaſe) of the other.</p>
            <p>And ſeeing the other is meerly compoſed of parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular Relations, and brings not any thing to direct the recollection of the affairs of <hi>England,</hi> there are
<pb facs="tcp:165575:3"/>added ſome Obſervations, by which it may appear, with what Sympathie the affairs of the Engliſh Court and Iriſh Rebels, were carried on. And with what impiety Great ones warp from their true and pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick Intereſt, to ſacrifice to their private Ambi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, by unlawfull compliances, and bloudy permiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions.</p>
            <p>This is that <hi>(Reader)</hi> which in <hi>Limine</hi> I was to tell you; and I doubt not, but this ſmall piece will heighten thy expectation of the greater volume, which with all diligence ſhall be haſtened to thee.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="history">
            <pb facs="tcp:165575:4"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:165575:4"/>
            <head>THE HISTORY of the IRISH REBELLION.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He Rebellion in <hi>Ireland,</hi> which brake forth in the year 1641. was in its deſign ſo divelliſn, in its attempt ſo ſudden, and in its execution ſo Sanguinary: That neither that evening which to this day infames <hi>Sicilly,</hi> nor the vaſt profuſion of bloud, about a Centry of years ſince, made at <hi>Paris,</hi> do by many degrees come near the inhumanity and deaths by this one action, which is therefore ſo neceſſary to be known, as well to thoſe who are not well verſed in the Iriſh affairs, as alſo thoſe that are hurried away in the torrent of falſe aſſeverations, or drawn aſide by reaſon of the ſpetious pretences of the Iriſh Party and their Complices, that wee can not think we
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:165575:5"/>diſcharge our duty, if we let not all ſober Chriſtians underſtand by this extract taken from ſeveral depoſitions, upon oath before the Commiſſioners in that behalf authorized by Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion under the great Seal of <hi>Ireland.</hi> What a meek Religion it is, how conſtant to that ſweet ſimplicity and innocence, taught and practiſed by <hi>Ieſus Chriſt,</hi> and followed in the primitive ages. I ſay, what a meek Religion it is, that from its own principles, can naturally and without force draw ſuch fierce and bloudy concluſions, and how fit they are to be Members of mankind, much leſſe to receive protectionall favor, that implicitly reſign themſelves to the perpetration of that which the ſowers of ſuch wicked ſeed ſhall propoſe unto them.</p>
            <p>Yet are we not to ſuppoſe, that that fatall erup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion was ſo ſudden as it appeared, or ſo unpre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meditated, as not to have been the obſtinate and reſtleſſe deſign of many yeares. Nor yet that the Iriſh though a people changeable, and ſuſcep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table of commotion) had ſo much either courage, diſcretion, and induſtry, as to have attempted this without ſtrong influences, ſerious debates, and conſtant quickenings.<note place="margin">See all the depoſitions under the head for the antiquity of the Plot, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the first head of all.</note> No it is now 25, or 26 years ſince Hell firſt breathed out (by means of the Romiſh Clergy) this cruel machination, and inſpired them with an expedient how to deſtroy Proteſtantiſm, firſt within <hi>England, Ireland,</hi> and <hi>Scotland;</hi> and afterwards in what ends of the world ſoever it, That is to ſay the ſincere word of Sal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:165575:5"/>ſhould bee taught and profeſſed.</p>
            <p>But becauſe in the three lands of <hi>England, Scot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi>
               <note place="margin">This was confeſſed by a Frier to one M. <hi>George Stoc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dale</hi> in the County of <hi>Dublin,</hi> for which ſee M. <hi>Stoedales</hi> ſecond exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mination in the book of <hi>Dublin,</hi> he being the <hi>165.</hi> depon.</note> and <hi>Ireland,</hi> it was moſt generally and prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipally obſerved. It was firſt projected and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolved amongſt theſe of the Roman Party, that with the leaſt noiſe and ſuſpition poſſible, much Arms, Ammunition, Artillery, Shipping, and great ſums of mony (the very ſinews of War) with ſtrong numbers of Commanders and Souldiers, ſhould be raiſed and had in readineſſe in <hi>Spain,</hi> and <hi>Italy,</hi> for the aſſaulting and ſurpriſing of <hi>Ire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>To the promoting whereof, great ſums of mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny were levied at <hi>Rome,</hi> and divers other parts both of <hi>Italy,</hi> and <hi>Spain,</hi> eſpecially amongſt their Convents, Colledges, and Religious houſes. And becauſe that forreign power and proviſion might be the more prevalent,<note place="margin">See alſo the dep. of M. <hi>Roger Hol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> Coun. <hi>Monoghan</hi> both taken about eight years ſince.</note> &amp; tranſported with the leaſt oppoſition. It was further projected and agreed a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt theſe confederates. That all commotions &amp; ſedition poſſible, ſhould be raiſed by the Prieſts &amp; Friers (too numerous and powerfull at that time) both in <hi>England, Scotland,</hi> and <hi>Ireland,</hi> between the Proteſtants and the Papiſts. Whereupon (though too many were there before) yet great ſwarms of Prieſts &amp; Friers flew into the ſame three lands out of <hi>Spain, Italy, France, Flanders,</hi> and other places. Who were ſo intent, ſollicitous, cloſe, and ſubtile in their courſes, as men long bred &amp; verſed therein. That upon their ſecret and ſubtile ſurmiſes of danger there threatned by the Puritan party (as
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:165575:6"/>they call them) to the Proteſtant party, to their (the Romiſh) Religion, whoſe (as they pretended) ſubverſion was their principall aim) much diſſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and differences aroſe and for a long time boil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed and burned in the breaſts of great numbers, ſome naturally wicked, others (perhaps) onely ſeduced and ſurprized, ignorantly following the time and their acquaintances, that on a ſudden (af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter ſeveral years ſpent in broaching and ſowing of theſe jealouſies, and in preparing of the other pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſion) while the harmeleſſe Proteſtant thought leaſt, onely hoped to be quiet, there were ſent out of <hi>Spain</hi> a ſtrong fleet of ſhips fully manned, with great numbers of Commanders, Souldiers and Mariners, and as well fraught and furniſhed with Artilery, Arms, Amunition, Money and all other neceſſaries for Warre; all which were de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigned for <hi>Ireland:</hi> One half to be landed at <hi>Kinſale</hi> in the South-weſt, the other half at <hi>Kil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>labegges</hi> in the North. Howbeit a fierce and ſtrong wind carrying them (perforce) paſt the Coaſt of <hi>Ireland</hi> into the Narrow Sea, the <hi>Hollanders</hi> fell upon them, and as it is well known, ſunk many, took divers, yet ſome eſcaped.</p>
            <p>This plot thus farre (by the great Providence) prevented, the Rebellion could not then begin in <hi>Ireland,</hi> (as indeed it ſhould have done) had the fleet (as was intended) landed there.</p>
            <p>Whereupon afterwards it was further plotted and agreed amongſt thoſe Machivillian Factors, of <hi>Spain</hi> and <hi>Rome,</hi> and many other Lay-Papiſts
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:165575:6"/>of <hi>England, Scotland</hi> and <hi>Ireland,</hi> (all ſworn to ſecreſie) and ſtill, (notwithſtanding that their high diſaſter) as much as they could, keeping their former plot and reſolution on foot.</p>
            <p>That in all thoſe three Lands,<note place="margin">See the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition of M. <hi>Thomas Crant</hi> of the County of <hi>Cavan</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers.</note> the Papiſts ſhould generally riſe up in arms upon one ſet day, &amp; then to ſurpriſe the tower of <hi>London</hi> in <hi>England,</hi> the Caſtle of <hi>Edenburgh</hi> in <hi>Scotland,</hi> and the Caſtle of <hi>Dublin</hi> in <hi>Ireland,</hi> with as many more Caſtles, Forts, Holds and places of ſtrength, as they could poſſibly feaze upon in all the three Lands. And the better to enable themſelves to ſurpriſe the Caſtle and City of <hi>Dublin,</hi> it was concluded, that twenty Popiſh Souldiers out of every County of the Land, ſhould (the night before the time appointed for the taking of <hi>Dublin,</hi>) privately make their addreſſes to that City, the Suburbs and other places there about, to be in readineſſe to aſſiſt the taking and ſpoyling of the ſame Caſtle and Citty, and to do execution upon the Proteſtants, which numbers of men, and many more came thither at the time appointed; a great part whereof crept into the City and Suburbs, the night before; the reſidue remained about the Ditches, Hedges &amp; ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcure places there, as fully appeared on the Greens of that Citty the next morning, to the great terror of the honeſt Citizens. And alſo becauſe they might not want full ſtrength to perform and bear out their deſign, they took occaſion to make uſe of another force raiſed there, upon pretence to be ſent to forreign ſervice: ſome of
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:165575:7"/>which they practiſed, ſhould be brought up to take ſhipping at <hi>Dublin,</hi> and thereabout lye in readineſſe, and the reſt to lye in other parts near the Port towns of <hi>Ireland;</hi> all to countenance and back the buſineſſe. They taking the advantage of certain Commiſſions, (all dated about <hi>May</hi> 1641 granted by the King to ſeverall Commanders, <hi>viz.</hi> One to Colonell <hi>Garret Barrie,</hi> another to Colonel <hi>Tibbot Taaff.</hi> (now Lord <hi>Taaff</hi>) ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to Col. <hi>Iohn Barrie.</hi> another to Sir <hi>Jeames Dillon</hi> (all Iriſh Papiſts) for raiſing &amp; levying for each of theſe Colonells 1000. menin <hi>Ireland,</hi> out of thoſe men formerly raiſed in that land by the Earl of <hi>Strafford,</hi> and then lately disbanded. The ſame Commiſſions purporting, that they ſhould be tranſported for the ſervice of any Forreign Prince in Amitie with the King, the rather to free <hi>Ireland</hi> of them.</p>
            <p>Theſe Commiſſions were in <hi>Iuly</hi> afterwards, (which was about three moneths before the breaking out of the Rebellion) brought over and delivered by theſe Colonels to the Lord Juſtices, and Councel of <hi>Ireland,</hi> whereupon four thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand of the disbanded ſouldiers aforeſaid were raiſed, one Regiment whereof under the comand of the ſaid Colonel <hi>Iohn Barrie</hi> was brought to the parts near <hi>Dublin,</hi> the reſt to other Ports of <hi>Ireland,</hi> and there (for a ſeeming defect of tranſportation and proviſion) they hanckered and ſtayed for a good time, yet ſeeming daily to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pare, but the <hi>Iriſh</hi> Popiſh Knights and other Bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geſſes
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:165575:7"/>of the Parliament, (finding the Lord Juſtices and Councel forward to ſend them a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way) moved extreamly in the Parliament Houſe, that they might not go out of the Land till the Kings pleaſure ſhould be further known.</p>
            <p>The Lord Juſtices and Councel being thus ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treamly importuned by the Parliament (then grown ſtrong in Iriſh) were drawn to write into <hi>England,</hi> ſignifying the Parliaments earneſt deſire therein, yet gave no impediment to the going of thoſe Regiments, who in truth were ſufficiently retarded by the vehement labour of Prieſts and Jeſuites, and ſome of the Parliament Papiſts a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt thoſe Commanders, ſo as they continued there (for the moſt part) till the Rebellion brake out. And then perceiving their plot for ſurpri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zing of <hi>Dublin</hi> to be prevented,<note place="margin">Many Iriſh and other stangers hovered in <hi>England</hi> and <hi>London,</hi> and the Suburbs the ſame time, as <hi>I</hi> have been credibly in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed.</note> they and all thoſe before mentioned, which came out of all the Counties, as aforeſaid, unto, and about <hi>Dublin,</hi> diſperſed, and afterward became dexterous and ready actors in the inſuing rebellion.</p>
            <p>And although by divine providence this Plot were prevented in <hi>England,</hi> and <hi>Scotland,</hi> yet how it began and took effect in <hi>Ireland,</hi> is too well known to thoſe many eye witneſſes who were inhumanly turned out of their eſtates, and expo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed to all the miſeries of cold, wet, and hunger, if not (for increaſe of their miſeries) ſharply wound<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed and maimed; and was too well felt by others, whoſe lives were torn and rent from them in this day of viſitation, appearing by the numerous exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minations.</p>
            <pb n="8" facs="tcp:165575:8"/>
            <p> And before I make mention of the other things which you ſhall find in the enſuing tract, give me leave to ſay ſomewhat of that, delivered upon Oath by that Reverend and learned Preacher <hi>Henry Iones</hi> Doctor in Divinity (as he heard it ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſed and confeſſed unto him by two Friers) Who relateth,<note place="margin">See the exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mination of Dr. <hi>Henry Iones,</hi> Com. <hi>Dublin 337.</hi> dep.</note> that howſoever the firſt breaking out of the fire of this rebellion into a flame began but the 23 of <hi>October</hi> 1641. yet was it ſmoaking many years before. God having given many glimpſes for the diſcovery of it, had they been du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly conſidered or proſecuted, to a diſcovery.</p>
            <p>For firſt, about three or four years before the Rebellion began to break out (amongſt many pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hibited books brought into the City of <hi>Limerick</hi> from forreign parts, and ſeized on by the Reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rend man Doctour <hi>Web</hi> then Biſhop there) amongſt the reſt one was framed as an addition to the firſt part, which was printed conteining a diſcourſe of the Friers of the <hi>Auguſtine</hi> Order, ſometime ſeat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in the Town of <hi>Armagh</hi> in <hi>Vlſter,</hi> but by rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of the times, at that preſent reſident, (as the writing imported) in the City of <hi>Limerick</hi> in <hi>Mun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter,</hi> that whileſt that Convent flouriſhed at <hi>Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>magh,</hi> it was protected and largely provided for by the then Earl of <hi>Tirone;</hi> ſince whoſe expulſion out of <hi>Ireland,</hi> that Convent was alſo decayed, and driven to thoſe diſtreſſes it did for the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent complain to undergo: yet that within three years <hi>Ireland</hi> ſhould find, that the ſaid Earl had a ſon, inheriting his fathers virtues, who ſhould re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtore
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:165575:8"/>that Kingdome to its former liberty, and that Covent to its firſt Luſtre.</p>
            <p>About the ſame time a Popiſh Prieſt at <hi>Lime<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rick</hi> aforeſaid gave out that within three years there ſhould not be a Proteſtant in <hi>Ireland.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>About the ſame time alſo one <hi>Walter Newgent</hi> of <hi>Rathaſpick</hi> in the County of <hi>Meath</hi> Gentleman, ſon to <hi>Walter Newgent</hi> Eſquire (a man of good fortunes) upbraiding an Iriſh Proteſtant who was a Pariſh Clark, with his Religion, and both ſpeak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Latine, the ſaid <hi>Newgent</hi> uttered theſe words, <hi>Infra tres annos veniunt tempus &amp; potentiâ in</hi> Hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bernia <hi>quando tu longe</hi> (likely meaning <hi>diu</hi>) <hi>pen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>debis in cruce propter Diabolicam Veſtram Religio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nem.</hi> The party to which this was ſpoken (fearing the power of the man) durſt not ſpeak of it, onely in private, but being examined judicially, depoſed the ſame.</p>
            <p>About the ſame time, near the <hi>Naas</hi> about 12 miles from <hi>Dublin,</hi> a Papiſt Prieſt newly arri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved out of <hi>Flanders,</hi> enformed the Lord Deputy <hi>Strafford</hi> of an intercourſe of Letters, between the young Earle of <hi>Tirone</hi> with others in <hi>Flanders,</hi> and the then Popiſh Primate of <hi>Armagh, Rely,</hi> concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing an invaſion within a ſhort time intended upon <hi>Ireland.</hi> The Prieſt offering (ſo his perſon might be ſecured) to direct ſuch as ſhould be there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unto appointed to the place, where the letters lay in the Cuſtody of the ſaid <hi>Rely: Rely</hi> was there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon ſent for together with the Popiſh Vicar generall of <hi>Armagh,</hi> both were committed to
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:165575:9"/>the Caſtle of <hi>Dublin,</hi> but ſoon after releaſed, and the informer diſmiſſed with ten pounds, a ſuit of clothes and ſome other reward. Thus far Doctor <hi>Iones.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>It appeareth alſo by the examinations that many other informations were given of an intended Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bellion to the ſaid Lord of <hi>Strafford,</hi> and to Sir <hi>George Radcliffe</hi> Knight, ſeverall years before it brake out from ſeverall parts of <hi>Ireland.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>For we find it proved that about <hi>April,</hi>
               <note place="margin">See Dr. <hi>Maxwells</hi> dep. Coun. <hi>Armagh.</hi>
               </note> 1638. one Prieſt <hi>Mac-Caſy,</hi> came from <hi>Rome</hi> with the Popes Bull for the Pariſh of <hi>Tinon,</hi> and being kept out by Sir <hi>Phelim ô Neal,</hi> he talked freely of a Rebellion plotted and intended by Sir <hi>Phelim</hi> and others, and told the then Lord Deputy <hi>Strafford</hi> thereof at <hi>Dublin.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>One Mr. <hi>Richard Parſons</hi> a Miniſter,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>See Mr.</hi> Ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chard Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons <hi>dep. Coun.</hi> Cavan.</note> was told by four ſeverall perſons of credit (which he namelth) three years and above before the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bellion, that the plot for the intended Rebellion was diſcovered to the then Lord Deputy (which was the Lord of <hi>Strafford</hi>) by one that was ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vant to Sir <hi>Phelim ô Neal,</hi> and that thereupon the Popiſh titularie Primate of <hi>Ireland,</hi> was ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehended and impriſoned at <hi>Dublin,</hi> but after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards procured favour to be enlarged, ſo as he heard no further enquiry made after it, untill the fire thereof brake out into a flame, which other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe might have been prevented, and thereby the lives of many poor innocent people ſaved, that were murthered and taken away, beſides the common
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:165575:9"/>calamitie, waſting and depopulating of the Land prevented.</p>
            <p>And it is much to be preſumed,<note place="margin">James Stew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>art <hi>Coun.</hi> Cavan.</note> that the <hi>Iriſh</hi> had too much influence from the Lord of <hi>Straf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ford,</hi> for that ſome of them divulged, that one cauſe of their inſurrection, was the cutting off of the Lord Lieutenant, proteſting that ſuch as were <hi>Britanes</hi> ſhould pay for it.</p>
            <p>Another inſtance thereof is,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Mr.</hi> George Creichtoun <hi>Coun.</hi> Cavan.</note> that one Mr. <hi>John Bellowe</hi> being ſent by the houſe of Commons of <hi>Ireland</hi> to proſecute the Earl of <hi>Strafford</hi> in the Parliament of <hi>England,</hi> and telling the buſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs to the Earl of <hi>Niddesdale,</hi> that Earl migh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tily diſwaded him with theſe words, <hi>If he be ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken away our Ctholique Religion cannot ſtand, for the caſe is ſo with us now, that if he live, we hope to do well, if he miſcarry we are all undone.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Another inſtance hereof we have from one Mirs. <hi>Champin,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Alice Cham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pin <hi>Coun.</hi> Fermanagh.</note> who (having been robbed of a ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry great eſtate, and her husband and many others in her houſe murthered, the Rebels tould her that the Earl of <hi>Strafford</hi> was the Plotter of that their riſing, and that if the ſaid Earl had been li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving, they ſhould not have had ſo much trouble in vanquiſhing of <hi>Ireland,</hi> as they had.</p>
            <p>Another hint we have both of the antiquity of the Plot for the Rebellion, and of ſomewhat concerning the Earl of <hi>Strafford,</hi> and the Lord of <hi>Derries</hi> knowing of it, which is this;<note place="margin">Roger Hol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land <hi>Coun.</hi> Monoghan.</note>
            </p>
            <p>One Mr. <hi>Roger Holland</hi> an <hi>Engliſh</hi> Gentleman of good value (after he was robbed of a good
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:165575:10"/>eſtate by the <hi>Iriſh</hi>) fled towards <hi>Dublin,</hi> and comming to the <hi>Newry,</hi> and <hi>Carlingford,</hi> was in both places in company with Colonel <hi>Richard Plunket,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Note that this was in the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of the Rebellion, <hi>1641.</hi>
               </note> (a notable active Rebel) who there told him and many others, that the ſaid plot had been for ſeventeen years then paſt in contriving, and that Frier <hi>Melone</hi> and himſelf, and one of the Lord <hi>Trimbleſtons</hi> ſons (another Frier) with many others of the Nobility of the Palle, and in the North knew of it a long time, but that ſome others of the Nobles knew not of it till of late, and as for Sir <hi>Phelim ô Neal,</hi> he made no account (as he ſaid) but for all <hi>Ireland</hi> to be his own and the others of his party, for that was their in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent, and for all Puritans and Proteſtants they ſhould all ſuffer, but ſuch as ſhould goe to <hi>Maſs,</hi> and but few of them ſhould be left, but thoſe that knew of the aforeſaid plot, which was part<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly the Biſhop of <hi>Derry,</hi> for whom they daily wiſhed, for he was the onely man of the <hi>Engliſh</hi> which they loved beſt. And that if they had him, he ſhould take no hurt. And heartily wiſhed that the late Lord Lieutenant were alive, for if he had lived, they had lived well enough, and would have had all the ſtrength in the Kingdome. And that he knew very well of their plot, which was the cauſe for removing the pieces of Ordnance out of the North.</p>
            <p>Some other canſes are mentioned for remove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of the Artilerie out of the North, and other places, which are but foul Symptomes of any
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:165575:10"/>care his Lordſhip took of the ſafety of the <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh</hi> there, but for thoſe, I leave you to the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aminations themſelves.</p>
            <p>I think theſe inſtances may ſatisfie any judi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious and impartial man, that this plot is not of any late conception or contrivance, as the <hi>Iriſh</hi> Papiſts and ſome others of their faction, would wreſt it unto: Which is, That the beginning and occaſion of it, was but taken from a pretended knowledge, or feigned information they had; That this preſent Parliament of <hi>England</hi> had de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creed to deſtroy all the Papiſts, both of <hi>England, Scotland</hi> and <hi>Ireland,</hi> which was and is a pretence as vain, as they ſhameleſs in broaching it. But it is a cuſtome amongſt the Diſciples of Sathan, (no leſſe frequent than ſubtile) never to act any thing of high concernment, and ſpecially to put nothing in execution, without knowing firſt how to palliate and excuſe it, by ſome ſeeming and more than ordinary neceſſity. And who ſo fit to contrive a ſecond, when the firſt plot and excuſe would rather amaze and deterre the multitude with home they were to deal, than engage their faith therein, than that old wilie Serpent and lyar from the beginning, and the Romiſh locuſts, his accompliſhed Artiſts, who contrived a way, and in ſhew a cauſe of neceſſity for a ſudden in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurrection of the <hi>Iriſh</hi> againſt the <hi>Engliſh</hi> and Proteſtants, as it were for ſaving of their own throats from a preſent pretended conſpiracy a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt them, made by the <hi>Engliſh.</hi> And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:165575:11"/>not to rely ſolely upon their own or the forreign ſtrength they expected to reſiſt it. It was then further reſolved and agreed on amongſt them, That howſoever the ground-work of this Rebellion was laid very many years ſince,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Dr.</hi> Henry Jones <hi>Com.</hi> Dublin.</note> (as they had done the like in ſeveral former ages) yet would they not have it ſo to ſeem. But new occaſion muſt be found as the ſole cauſe of their breaking out.</p>
            <p>The fitteſt means for this, (as they concei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved) was to caſt Aſperſions upon the Sate and preſent government, which (if longer tolerated) would (as they gave out) prove extreamly danger<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous, not onely to their Religion, but to their Lives and poſterity; For effecting where of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ports were caſt out, that in the Parliament of <hi>England,</hi> the cutting off of al the Papiſts in <hi>Ireland</hi> of what degree ſoever was concluded on; and the execution of that reſolution commited to the Councel of <hi>Ireland.</hi> Who (ſay they) appoint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed a day for this work, being the 23 of <hi>Novem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber</hi> then next following 1641. That for the bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, more ſure, and ſecret managing of this pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended plot, ſuch of the popiſh Nobility and gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try of both houſes, as appeared in Parliament at <hi>Dublin,</hi> ſhould be ſecured, (no ſuch thing being ſo much as thought on by that State) and for the drawing together the reſt, (amongſt other pretences) This is alledged to be one, that the Kings-Rents were purpoſely omitted, and not cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led upon in Eaſter-Term with that earneſtneſs
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:165575:11"/>as formerly. And that ſuch as made default ſhould be ſummoned to appear in Michaelmas Term in <hi>Dublin,</hi> and there ſurpriſed. Whereby ſuch of them as ſhould then remain in the coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tries (wanting their Heads) might be (as they ſaid) eaſily cut off. They ſaid this preſent plot was (I know not how) diſcovered unto them, ſo that for the ſafety of their lives and profeſſions, they were enforced to ſtand upon their guard, and to counter-work that day of the 23 of <hi>No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vember,</hi> by their declaring and riſing themſelves in Arms on the 23 of <hi>October,</hi> a moneth before. The time drawing near for putting their deſign in execution, there was a great meeting appoint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, of the heads of the Romiſh Clergie, and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Lay-men of their faction, at the Abbey of <hi>Multifarnam</hi> in the County of <hi>Weſtmeath,</hi> where was a Covent of <hi>Franciſcan</hi> Friers. This meeting happened accordingly, not long before the time of the breaking out of their Rebelion, where the buſineſs then in queſtion was, what courſe ſhould be taken with the <hi>Engliſh,</hi> and all others that were found in the whole Kingdom to be Proteſtants. The Councel was therein devided, ſome were for their baniſhment, without attempting on their lives. Others urged a neceſſity of cutting off them and theirs, and that a generall Maſsacre were the ſafeſt and readieſt way to free the Kingdom of all fears and dangers; Others moved a mean way, neither to diſmiſſe nor kill, yet thoſe that moſt favoured them concluded that they ſhould
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:165575:12"/>be all robbed and ſtripped, and according to this do we find the event and courſe of their proceed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings. For in ſome places, they were generally put to the ſword, ſome reſtrained their perſons, others (after a time) diſmiſsed their priſoners, firſt having ſpoyled them of their goods, and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed them to cold and famine, they that way pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſhed by the worſt death of all. And becauſe no neceſſarie thing fit for ſo gracious a Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealth ſhould be left unſetled: Theſe mighty Counſellors (conſiſting for the moſt part of ancient <hi>Engliſh</hi> Papiſts) diſcourſed to eſtabliſh certain rules or laws for the Civil or Martial government of the Land, concluding that from thenceforth no Proteſtant at all, ſhould either rule, or have any being there. They alſo con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluded, that when they ſhould have ſetled the Land, they would ſend thirty thouſand men into <hi>England,</hi> to joyn with the <hi>Spaniſh</hi> and other for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, and then joyntly to fall upon <hi>Scotland,</hi> for re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ducing both thoſe Lands to the obedience of the Pope, which being finiſhed, they had enga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged themſelves to the King of <hi>Spain,</hi> for aſſiſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing him againſt the <hi>Hollanders,</hi> and giving their Rebellion (as they tearm it) its due correction.</p>
            <p>We find alſo that after theſe Prieſts and Friers had layd their firſt Plot, they committed and communicated the ſecrets of it to ſome of the Nobility, a good time after to ſome more of them, laſt of all to the Popiſh gentry of beſt value, (upon oaths of ſecreſy) and to live and
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:165575:12"/>die with them in the quarrel, and for a long time before the Rebellion, as well the powerful ones (who knew of the plot) as the reſt of the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſts, by command and direction of their Popiſh Prieſts and Friers, were obſerved in all parts of the Land to keep many ſtrict Faſts, and many of the meaner ſort being asked why they faſted ſo very often, their anſwers were, they knew not, but their holy Fathers told them, there was a good and great work, for the proſperity whereof, they muſt uſe much faſting and prayer.</p>
            <p>One day of their humiliation and praying, being the more remarkable, becauſe generally perform<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by them in all places. The publick prayer of all their Prieſts and Friers then being, that God would give a bleſſing to the great deſign in hand, &amp; drawing near, and that he would vouchſafe ability unto them thorowly to effect the ſame. This drew the Common people into a unanimous expectation &amp; ſtrong reſolution to proſecute the ſame, when they ſhould diſcover to what end their ſaid Ghoſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly-Fathers had engaged their zeal. And although the times of their humiliatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> &amp; prayer were much obſerved by the Engliſh and Proteſtants, yet they harboured not the due ſuſpic on which the demea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nors of the other party required, becauſe (indeed) the Proteſtants imagined the Papiſts thereby poin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted at, &amp; meant the endeavors of the Iriſh Comiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſioners then in <hi>England,</hi> in purſuit of thoſe graces &amp; great bounties they afterward obteined fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the King, &amp; brought over with the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. And noted it is, that
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:165575:13"/>this ſo ſtrict humilliation and praying was not onely in <hi>Ireland,</hi> but frequently obſerved by many of the Papiſts in <hi>England.</hi>
               <note place="margin">The Popes Nuncio di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rected the like fast to be then in <hi>England,</hi> as appears by the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claration of the Parlia<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ment.</note> And yet to the vulgar ſort of people therof was not diſcovered, only their Ghoſtly-Fathers, their Prieſts, and Friers (to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe and inflame their devotion) gave them a hint, that ſtrict faſting and diligent fervent prayers, muſt be performed by all Romiſh Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholiques (as they call them) for the proſperity of a great deſign they had in hand. And here I can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not paſs by, but muſt tender to your conſideratio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, a Letter found at <hi>Preston</hi> in <hi>Lanca-ſhire,</hi> written by a Papiſt to one Mr. <hi>Weſthy</hi> a Doctor in Phiſick of the ſame Religion. Whereby he was not onely enjoined alone, but alſo to ſtir up the zeal and af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection of others (Papiſts) to obſerve a ſtrict con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant faſt, and praying for the proſperity of the Queens good intentions, which by the opinions of the Judicious, was meant nothing elſe, than the Plot above mentioned.</p>
            <p>But leſt I ſhould prove deficient in relating ſome part of the plot of theſe incarnate Divels, above mentioned, I ſhall deſire you to take along with you this known truth.<note place="margin">See all the depoſitions under this Head.</note> That their deſign likewiſe was, not to ſpare any of the Engliſh race, that were Proteſtants (as in the ſeverall Rebelli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons before they had likewiſe reſolved to do.) And that they would deprive of life all irrationall creatures of the Engliſh breed, as horſes, cattell, ſheep, ſwine, &amp; even very cats and dogs. They alſo deſigned to annull and deſtroy all the Laws, Cuſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tomes,
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:165575:13"/>Civillity, Manners and Apparell of the Engliſh; to deface and ſpoil all their Churches, and all Monuments, Records, Charters, Writings, any way relating thereto; and either to ſeize, or deface all Forts, Caſtles, Holds, Houſes, Towns, and all things whatſoever either erected by, held, or belonging unto the Engliſh &amp; other Proteſtants, or otherwiſe tending to civility. And laſtly, to aboliſh and abjure all Engliſh rule, dominion, Magiſtracy, and government whatſoever.</p>
            <p>But ſome may ſay, I ſtay too long in relating their agreements and damned confederacy, before I come to their actions. 'Tis true I do, conſidering the worſt of their actions are over, otherwiſe if the execution could not have taken effect, untill I had ended the relation of their plot, I ſhould chooſe to be writing thereof, <hi>Vſque ad necem.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But the day limited for the beginning their blou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy Maſſacre, <hi>viz.</hi> the 23 of <hi>October</hi> 1641. came, and then upon a ſudden, when the innocent hears of the Proteſtant Engliſh, ſeemed to aſſume to themſelves full ſecurity. Theſe barbarous peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple like Lions, or Tigars, generally fell upon them all, in all the Counties of the Province of <hi>Vl<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter,</hi> and in ſome other Counties of that Land, as in ſome parts of the Provinces of <hi>Lemſter</hi> and <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naght,</hi> and there committed the unheard of and ſavage cruelties mentioned in the ſame examinati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, ſome perſons onely (which indeed are ſo few, that hardly one of forty) by ſtrange means
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:165575:14"/>or rare convoys,<note place="margin">See the dep. under the Head cont cerning mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers crucl<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </note> eſcaped to <hi>Dublin</hi> or other Gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſons there to recount their miſeries: From which ſmall number indeed we gathered the ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count we have of the miſerable ſufferings of themſelves and the reſt. But howſoever many of the Proteſtants of the Province of <hi>Vlſter</hi> and other parts, were murthered or ſpoiled at the very firſt: yet becauſe the Lord <hi>Macquire,</hi> Mr. <hi>Maghan,</hi> and the reſt of that bloudy crew, had failed in the ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king of <hi>Dublin</hi> City and Caſtle, (which indeed took them) by occaſion of that happy diſcovery at the very inſtant, made by Mr. <hi>Owen Connelly,</hi> unto whom many thouſands of us (next unto God) ſtand engaged for no leſſe than our lives.</p>
            <p>Therefore the Lords, Knights, Gentlemen, and others of the Papiſts, of the Palle (being old Engliſh, and as deep in the confederacy as any of the meer Iriſh) were aſtoniſhed, and for the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent at a ſtand. And although they had ſtrong wills and affections, (according to their bloudy Covenant) to ſecond and join with the Northern Iriſh in their depredations, ſpoiling, and maſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cring of the Engliſh Proteſtants, yet were they deterred to ſhew themſelves in action with o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther confederates, untill they had gained ſome fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther experience, what the ſucceſſe might be.</p>
            <p>In the mean time becauſe they would encroach, and gain (as much as poſſibly they could) upon the Lords, Juſtices, and Privy-Councel of that land, (who then had not their Loyalties in ſuſpiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, knowing them to be ſo well ſetled and enrich<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:165575:14"/>as they were.) They (in a fawning manner ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply themſelves to that Counſel,<note place="margin">This is and wil be justi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied by all the then Privye Councel of <hi>Ireland,</hi> and I knew it my ſelf to be true.</note> ſeeming much to condole the begun Rebellion, and bloudy acts committed by the Iriſh, and withall proteſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing their harbouring of great fears, that they them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves ſhould be ſpoiled and periſh by them, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe the Councel would afford them ſome Arms and Ammunition. Omitting none of the greateſt vows, that they were loyal and true to the State, and would (as formerly their Ance<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtors had done) adventure their fortunes and lives with them and the Engliſh Proteſtants, and with them either live or periſh: upon which carneſt proteſtations, the Councel (being in that tickle time unwilling to ſtir jealouſies in them) furni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed many of the chief of thoſe Palle-men with ſome quantities of Arms and Ammunition, for guarding of their houſes, &amp; after aſſigned them Arms for 300 men, for the guarding and defend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of the County of <hi>Dublin,</hi> with the like pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portion of Arms, to raiſe men for the defending of <hi>Meath, Lowth, Kildare,</hi> and <hi>Weſt-Meath,</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the five ſhires of the Palle, and all inhabited with old Engliſh, intending therewith they ſhould reſiſt any further Northern incurſion. But on the contrary, by their underhand bringing in the Iriſh, they ſhortly after cut off ſome companies of newly banded Engliſh, ſent from <hi>Dublin</hi> to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward the relief of <hi>Droghedah,</hi> which was done in that (ever accounted) the moſt civill part of the Palle. Then did the Papiſts of the Palle eſteem
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:165575:15"/>it their time to break all faith and go into open re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bellion, wherein they joined with the meer bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>barous bloud-ſuckers of the North, turning the Arms, and Ammunition againſt thoſe, from whom ſo fraudulently they obtained them.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>D.</hi> Ro. Max<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wel <hi>County</hi> Armagh.</note> And then who more barbarous and ſierce than they, for then they told that bloud-thirſty (yet cowardly) Rebell Sir <hi>Phelim ô Neal,</hi> that there was neither room enough nor ſafety either for him or them ſo long as any of the Proteſtants were alive.</p>
            <p>This wicked force (ſo united) encreaſing their pride, malice, and envy; their rage, and force; out of <hi>England,</hi> (to repreſſe them) not comming, but being retarded, they fell upon the remaining Proteſtants that were not murthered, nor eſca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped, and cut off many of them, ſtripped and rob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bed all the reſt. This alſo gave further encourage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment to all other Iriſh and old Engliſh Papiſts of <hi>Connaght,</hi> and <hi>Munſter</hi> to proſecute the former de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſign and agreement for ſpoiling the Engliſh Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtants, within thoſe two Provinces, ſo as none eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caped robbing and ſtripping, many extreamly tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tured, and very many ſuffered death. And although you may amongſt the Examinations at large (when they are printed) find out the true relations of nu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merous, various, and moſt ſtrange tortures &amp; mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, ſuch (as I am confident) cannot be parallel'd by ſtory, in any former age or Country, where no manner of provocation can truly be alledged to be given, but rather all invitations of love: Yet the more to move you to read the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> at large. I ſhall give
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:165575:15"/>you ſome ſhort touches of a few of them, as they ſtand proved by teſtimony of witneſſes upon oath.</p>
            <p>Firſt you may ſee what vaſt numbers (after robbing and ſtripping naked) were murthered and periſhed, many by the ſwo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>rd,<note place="margin">See all the depoſitions under the Head for murthers and cruel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties.</note> many by han<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging drowning, ſtrangling, burning, in Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches, houſes, and other places, many buried quick, ſome baited and worried with dogs, ſome ſtoned to death, ſome thrown into boiling water, ſome roaſted at the fire, ſome their bowels go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red through their fundaments, ſome their bellies ripped up and their bowels pulled out, the ſkuls of ſome broken by twiſting ropes and withes about their heads, ſome having their backs, arms, thighes and leggs broken, and cut off, others moſt miſerably wounded, ſlaſhed and gored, and ſo left to languiſh, freez, and ſtarve in their blouds; ſome hanged up by the hair of their heads; little Children deprived of fathers and mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, crying, mourning, and famiſhing by their dead bodies; ſome poor infants rather drawing than ſucking their dead mothers breſts; none help<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, none relieving, and none putting them out of their pain; but as they lay gaſping upon the earth, ſuffering doggs, ſwine, and other raven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous creatures, to put an end to their miſeries by devouring of them.</p>
            <p>There may you find many, whoſe backs, leggs, or thighs, being broken, and ſo diſabled to ſtir, lying in the fields, and having like beaſts eaten
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:165575:16"/>all the graſſe round about them, would after two or three days, deſire the Iriſh (comming to rejoice and glory over their miſeries) to kill and put them out of their pain; if they granted this cour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſie, it was rare, to ſome it was denied, onely they would change their paſture in carrying them where more graſs was, not ſo much to feed or re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve them, as to prolong their pining miſery. <hi>A cruell mercy!</hi>
            </p>
            <p>There you may find the Iriſh which were ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants, inſulting, robbing, torturing, wounding, and reviling their Engliſh late Maſters, who fed them from their infancies.</p>
            <p>There may you find poor women hanging by their necks, and their children alſo about their necks, ſome at their girdles, and (in ſcorn) dogs and cats hanging up with them.</p>
            <p>There you may find many poor Chriſtian Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts forced through holes under the ice, &amp; there drowned; and many purſued and pricked forward with pikes ſo far into the Sea, and others into other waters where that they were alſo drowned; &amp; many as they ſwam to the ſhore knocked on the heads, and run through with pikes, and ſo turned into the water again and drowned.</p>
            <p>There you may find the demoliſhed houſes, Churches, Caſtles, and other buildings lie full of dead-ſlaughtered bodies of Proteſtants unburied, and thoſe that were covered with earth, had (for the moſt part) old banks pulled upon them in dit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches,
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:165575:16"/>others lay ſtinking above ground infecting the air, except ſuch as doggs and ravenous crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures devoured.</p>
            <p>There may you find poor harmleſſe little chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren wounded, and then hanged up by the fleſh up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on tenter-hooks.</p>
            <p>There ſhall you find a poor Chriſtian Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant brought in naked laid upon a board, and the I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſh inſulting, after dinner drawing their ſwords, and at every healths drinking giving him a gaſh or wound (but not mortall) untill his whole body becommeth as it were one generall wound, and thereafter they caſt him upon a Dung-hill, there to die partly of his wounds and partly of famine, none daring to relieve him.</p>
            <p>There may be found how the ſavage Iriſh took a wooden prick or broach, and thruſt it up into the fundament of a Proteſtant, and then after draw him about the room with a joint ſtoole to force the broach, untill with extream pain, he ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther fainted or gave content to the ſpectators, by ſome notable ſkips and frisks.</p>
            <p>There may you find, a poor Proteſtant ſurpri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zed and (after ſtripping) his belly ripped up till they came to his ſmall guts, one end whereof they tied to a branch of a tree, and then forced him to turn round the tree till all his bowells were pulled out. The cruel Monſters then ſaying, they would then try, whether his guts or a dogs were longer.</p>
            <p>Other incredible barbarous acts of their graceles Children you may find: As their going abroad in
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:165575:17"/>great troops, armed with long wattles and whips, wherewith they would beat mens bodies about their privy-members, untill they beat or rather threſhed them off. And then returning with great joy to their Parents, were by them received for ſuch ſervice, as if it were in triumph. And where they found any ſlain women being with their fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces downward, thoſe they would turn upon their backs, and in great flocks reſort unto them; Cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuring all parts of their bodies but eſpecially ſuch as are not to be named, which afterwards they abuſed ſo many ways as chaſt ears would by no means hear.</p>
            <p>There you may find, their manner of ſhutting up in houſes, and Churches ſeverall great num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers of Proteſtants: And thoſe being ſtrongly guarded and kept in, had thoſe Churches and hou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes burned over their heads, and all they conſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med in the flame.</p>
            <p>There you may find, the bloudy butchers in a Church diſſecting and quartering the father and the ſon, and then throwing their quarters at the head of the much wounded mother.</p>
            <p>There you may find ſome proper Gentlewo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men hanged up by the hair of their heads in a tree a whole night and the next morning cut down, and life being found in them killed outright.</p>
            <p>There you may find three poor Proteſtant children (whoſe Parents were murthered) ſtrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped naked, and turned out of their late fathers houſe, and ſheltering themſelves in an Oven from
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:165575:17"/>the cold, fire was put after them, and there burned by the mercileſſe wretches.</p>
            <p>A great bellied woman with her little chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren, flying away to ſave their lives, ſhe by the fright and haſt was ſuddenly delivered of a Child, which the purſuers doggs eat up and devoured, thoſe villains there killing the Woman and the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Children.</p>
            <p>Severall Gentlewomens bellies ript up, when great with Child, their children ripped up out of their wombs, and in that poſture ſome hanged up.</p>
            <p>Some poor Gentlewomen in child-birth drow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned their children half born.</p>
            <p>Young children toſſed upon the Rebels pikes, who gloried in their deſtruction.</p>
            <p>Two Gentlewomen the daughters of a very a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged decrepit father (all ſtripped naked) enforced to ſupport their ſaid father under each arm, to a bog pit of water, where they were all drowned to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether.</p>
            <p>The wife enforced to kill the husband, the ſon the mother, the daughter to kill the brother, and ſtill the Rebels to kill the laſt bloud-ſhedder.</p>
            <p>There may you find very many Miniſters, ſome drowned, ſome their heads and hands cut off, as they were upon their knees, praying before death, ſome hanged, ſome ſmothered, ſome drawn to death at horſes tails, ſome tortured, fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſhed, put to the ſword, and others by various ways of torment cruelly brought to death.</p>
            <pb n="28" facs="tcp:165575:18"/>
            <p> There you may find, ſome Proteſtants (whom the blondy Aſſaſſinats found to be fat and corpu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent murthered, and Candles made of their greaſe.</p>
            <p>A good profeſſour of Gods truth was ſet and rammed upright in the earth all but the very head, to pine and ſtarve, till Crows and Ravens picked out his eys, and ravenous creatures devoured him.</p>
            <p>Great numbers buried quick, and one ſo intu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mulated, or kept in the earth with weight of ſtones and rubbiſh, that he cried out there a long time, his wife being lame, wounded and not able to help him out, yet ſcraped to his face, and to terminate his dolour (which ſhe could not help) tied a handkerchiff over his mouth, and ſo ſtop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped his breath.</p>
            <p>Very many good Proteſtants there were, ſome of which had the ſoals of their feet fried againſt the-fire, ſome affrighted with a block and a hat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chet, ſome drawn in a rope up and down the wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, ſome half hanged and letten down, ſome kept in the ſtocks till they rotted, many others cruelly tortured to confeſſe their moneys, oftentimes when they had none left.</p>
            <p>Many ſtript naked and impriſoned, there fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſhed and ſtarved, thoſe that ſurvived enduring hardſhip and miſeries unſpeakable.</p>
            <p>In finite numbers of Proteſtants (after fair quar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter promiſed, and ſworn to be given them) mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thered by heaps in moſt lamentable and inhuman manner.</p>
            <pb n="29" facs="tcp:165575:18"/>
            <p> The carcaſes and bones of many formerly de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceaſed, worthy Chriſtians, digged out of their graves, ſome caſt into ditches, ſome upon dung<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hils, others upon hedges, banks, fields and open places, deprived of ſuch buriall as was denyed to the late ſlaughtred Engliſh, the Rebels rejoycing to behold the bodies of the Engliſh in that condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, eſpecially the Miniſters, and the greateſt profeſſours of Gods truth. Which Carkaſes (as is here proved) theſe Barbarians caſt out like Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rion, or as the dead bodies of Doggs, or Swine, thereby ſhewing what baſe eſteem they had of them. And here this helliſh crew do greatly in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſult, and rejoyce at the deaths of the Lords Wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſes. Expreſſing ſuch their joy by ſending guifts and preſents one to another, as if they had received ſome great benefit, or had heard the moſt com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortable news. The like things made the Holy Ghoſt ſay, <hi>The dead bodies of thy ſervants have they given to be meat for the fowls of Heaven, and the fleſh of the Saints unto the beaſts of the earth.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I have here particularized but a very few of the barbarous cruelties, tortures, murthers and maſsacres exerciſed upon the Proteſtants, and Brittiſh; moſt, becauſe Proteſtants, ſome, becauſe Brittiſh, though Papiſts. All, becauſe Brittiſh. The wicked and cauſeleſs quarrel of the preſent Rebels, being as. well Nationall, and Perſonall, as their pretended Religion. But theſe few may (I believe) induce you to read over the reſt. The which becauſe you may with the more facility
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:165575:19"/>find out, I have drawn ſeverall heads of all their Plots, Deſignes, and actions, and of the ſufferings of the Engliſh and other Proteſtants, under each of which heads you ſhall find the names of the ſeveral Deponents or witneſses, proving the parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culars of the things contained, and concerned in the ſame; together with the places and Counties where thoſe Witneſses had reſidence.</p>
            <p>The Books of examinations being divided into Counties, and thoſe Counties into the ſeverall Provinces, of <hi>Vlſter, Lemſter, Connaght,</hi> and <hi>Mun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter.</hi> Wherein, by the way you may obſerve, that as this laſt Plot was chiefly at the firſt layd by the Romiſh Prieſts and Friers, ſo they, (after their fury was made viſible to the world) were the main actors, and bloudy executioners of moſt of the cruelties. Aſwel admoniſhing, as adminiſtring the Sacrament to the Souldiers, not to ſpare, but deſtroy the Engliſh and all Proteſtants. Amongſt which murthers and cruelties, it is to be obſerved, how the audacious Rebels often fell into high and threatning tearms, ſometimes againſt the High Court of Parliament in <hi>England,</hi> at other times againſt the Lords, Juſtices, and Councel of <hi>Ireland,</hi> againſt all Proteſtants in general, but principally againſt the Engliſh, all which they vowed to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroy: and for that purpoſe to ſend forces (after they ſhould have ſubdued and ſpoiled them in <hi>Ire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi>) into <hi>England,</hi> (as is afore mentioned,) with a full reſolution, that none ſhould draw breath but ſuch as ſhould acknowledge the Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>premacy
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:165575:19"/>of the Pope, and profeſſe the Romiſh Religion.</p>
            <p>And (which is to be much admired) the anci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent Engliſh of the Palle (being Papiſts) were by the inſtigation of the Prieſts and Friers, as much engaged in the Plot, and little leſſe in the action, than the meer Iriſh, and every way as cruell in the execution as they. The truth being, that without their concurrence and partaking, (which both in number, value, and power farre exceed the meer Iriſh) thoſe meer Iriſh (nevertheleſſe their inveterate and ſcornfull malice, and Brutiſh inſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lency) never could nor durſt have attempted any ſuch thing againſt the Engliſh at this time, but all joyning in confedracie, it was reſolved that the the Engliſh Proteſtants ſhould be deſtroyed, and looſe the Land of <hi>Ireland;</hi> And not ſo much as any living creature of the latter Engliſh race, per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted to have a being there. Inſomuch as ſome of our witneſses complain, That the degenerated Palle-Engliſh were moſt cruell amongſt the Brit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſh Proteſtants, never being ſatisfied with their bloud, untill they had in a manner ſeen the laſt drop thereof.</p>
            <p>And the more to engage the inferiours of all theſe confederates in their wicked action, both the meer Iriſh, and the old Engliſh Papiſts ſhew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in very many places a Parchment Writing with a broad ſeal thereunto, which they affirmed was a Commiſſion from the King for diſarming and deſtroying the Proteſtants, and for all that
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:165575:20"/>which they the Iriſh did. And becauſe that none ſhould ſtand out for want of ſeeing ſome autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity. The Prieſts, Friers, and others in two pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces (as is proved in imitation) of the ſaid origi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall Commiſſions, framed and produced ſeverall writings, purporting to be the Kings Commiſſion, or to that purpoſe. By occaſion whereof, all the rude multitude took further encouragement to execute their own wills, and wreak their cauſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe malice upon whom they pleaſed. Wherein they had no little aſſiſtance by their women and children. Who (as far as their power extended) were as active in cruelty as the men. So that the malice, ſtrength, and power of them all, was dilated to the full, in the deſtruction and deaths of the Proteſtant Engliſh, ſo far, that incredible numbers muſt needs be cut off. For by the monethly bills brought in by their Prieſts (as commanded by Sir <hi>Phelim ô Neal.</hi> It appeareth, that betwixt the beginning of the preſent Rebellion, and <hi>March</hi> then next enſuing, there were murthe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red and miſſing within the very Province of <hi>Vlster</hi> one hundred fifty four thouſand of the Britiſh Proteſtants, which being but one of the four Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinces, what might the numbers of thoſe extend unto of thoſe deſtroyed in the whole Land.</p>
            <p>All which murthers and cruelties the juſt God will now viſit, as hath already in a great mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure appeared, (the Lord be praiſed) both by the great and wonderful victories heretofore gained by our ſmall Armies at the ſeverall battels, firſt
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:165575:20"/>near <hi>Wicklo,</hi> after at <hi>Swords, Finglaſſe, Kilſalghan, Kikruſh, Liſnegarvy, Rockonell, Roſſe, Trim, Clancurry, Ballentobber, Liſcarrol, Knocknenott, Dunganhill, Dublin,</hi> and in ſeverall skirmiſhes in many parts of the Land, (wherein the Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments Armies, in reſpect of their numerous ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies were but as handfuls,) beſides the taking in and regaining of ſeverall ſtrong Garriſons, by ſmall forces, under the command of that emi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent and noble Collonel, <hi>Jones.</hi> Many of which, during the time of the unjuſt Treaty of peace, betwixt the Marqueſſe of <hi>Ormond</hi> and the Iriſh Rebells, were moſt wilfully (if not purpoſely) loſt unto, and ſurprized, by the Iriſh. And ſhall we not now look towards Heaven, bleſſe and praiſe the Lord of Hoſts, for thoſe, and the late glorious victories, which our noble and now brave army, have obtained ſince, under the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand of that moſt honoured and heroick ſpirit, the Lievtenant Generall of the Parliaments for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of <hi>England;</hi> and now the fortunate Lord Governour of <hi>Ireland,</hi> how proſperous, how victorious, how prevalent is he, and all thoſe both Commanders, and Souldiers under his con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duct? Witneſſe the winning of the ſtrong Tow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers of <hi>Droghedah, Dundalk, Trim, Arkloe, Wexford, Roſse, Kinſale, Cork, Youghall, Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rickfergus.</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>Beſides the taking in and regaining of very many ſtrong Garriſons, by the many skirmiſhes wherein the Parliaments parties have been ſtill
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:165575:21"/>victorious, againſt the enemies great multi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tudes.</p>
            <p>In all which the wonderfull hand of God hath been remarkably ſeen in ſtrengthning thoſe his faithfull inſtruments, to execute his juſt judgements againſt that bloudy and deceitfull ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neration, in whoſe skirts are found much bloud of Innocents.</p>
            <p>If Jeſuitical or Diobolical polices could have prevented the Engliſh forces, or retarded longer their going over with the now Lord Governour of <hi>Ireland</hi> (without doubt) it would have been done. All things for that end being attempted, that either meer man or the Divell could invent: For when all other ſhifts evaſions, doubts, projects, and wicked inventions could not prevaile, you may take notice what ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tile and Sophiſticall <hi>Queres</hi> they caſt out to dererre the Souldiers from going thither. Under which they have an inference of a ſuppoſed pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mary and moſt ancient right and intereſt of the meer Iriſh, to the Land of <hi>Ireland.</hi> Thereby (as much as poſſible) ſeeming to blemiſh the true and lawfull intereſt of the Engliſh to that Land; which the moſt intelligent men know well e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough, originally to have belonged to the Britiſh: and the Iriſh but a people that came to inhabite there by the permiſſion of the Britiſh. But for the better ſatisfaction of the ingenious reader in that behalf, I refer him to the anſwer and reſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lution made to thoſe <hi>Queres.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="27" facs="tcp:165575:21"/>
            <p> I cannot here paſſe by that Tradition, or rather (as many of the Iriſh tearm it) a Prophecy which they have (and for a long time have had) amongſt themſelves,<note place="margin">See Mrs. <hi>Suzanna Stockdale</hi> Com. <hi>Dub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lin</hi> her ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond exami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation. <hi>146.</hi> deponent.</note> proved by Mrs. <hi>Suſanna Stockdale</hi> in her depoſition, which is, That in the year 1649, the Iriſh ſhould weep over the Engliſh graves, which they had ſlaughtered. And that thoſe Iriſh ſhould all then be baniſhed, ſaving a few which ſhould be kept in vaſſalage by the Engliſh. How true this may prove I know not, nor would I therein engage any mans faith. But ſure I am that in all probability, their actions have meri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted both from God and man, and put them into the high ways of abſolute diſtruction, and fierceſt ven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geance which they might the more take into fear, did they but ſeriouſly receive into their thoughts what thoſe hideous cries of revenge againſt their murthers and other fatal meteors, ſigns,<note place="margin">See all the dep. under the head concerning Gods judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </note> and won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders in the firmament, the water, earth and fire (which have been ſeen and known to ſucceed their bloudy cruelties) do portend; and thereby be the more terrified to expect Gods heavy lay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing their iniquities on their own heads, the rather in that they have ſeen thoſe Articles of peace, made at ſeveral times by the Marqueſſe of <hi>Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mond</hi> with theſe Cannibals,<note place="margin">See the two ſeverall books of ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticles made by the Lord of <hi>Ormond.</hi>
               </note> (ſo diſtructive to the Proteſtant ſufferers, and their religion) and wherein ſuch large pardons and conceſſions are gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven to the Rebels, have been rendred fruitleſs, being juſtly condemned with ſuitable Anathames.) One of which Articles was that all inquiries, indict<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments,
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:165575:22"/>outlaryes, and other proceedings againſt theſe Rebels (whereof thoſe examinations were part) ſhould be vacated and extinguiſhed: which I am ſure had been done accordingly, to theſe ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aminations eſpecially, had they not ſecretly and on a ſudden been convayed away hither; which could not poſſibly have been done, had not an ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt and worthy Engliſh Marchant (at my re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſt) cloſely and covertly paſſed them away as Marchandize (amongſt other of his Goods) at that time, (ſo full of danger) when neither ſuch things, nor ſo much as a man muſt paſſe over out upon pain of death, without ſpeciall licence. Which all men might reſt confident, would not have been granted in that behalf by the then Lieu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenant the Earl of <hi>Ormond.</hi> But it pleaſed God they ſhould be tranſported to be publiſhed to the world. Whereby the juſtneſſe of the War now un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dertaken may be mantained, the deep ſufferings of the Engliſh and the execrable deſigns, plots, and act<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ions of the moſt inhuman and cruell Iriſh Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bels, may be manifeſted and left to poſterity, and the Common wealth of <hi>England</hi> now on this ſo pregnant provocation, and univerſall conſpiracy, reſolve (by Gods bleſſing) to ſettle a firm aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance to all thoſe Engliſh that ſhall hereafter ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venture to improve the Engliſh intereſt in <hi>Ire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> and at laſt put it into a caſe plentifully to retribute to <hi>England,</hi> for their moneys, deep expences of bloud and treaſure. Whereunto (the better to iuduce them) it may be taken
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:165575:22"/>into conſideration. That in all ages eſpecially, ſince about the middle of the reign of King <hi>Ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chard</hi> the ſecond, after the old Engliſh were de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>generated, when they could but obtain the leaſt opportunity or advantage, they have in every age raiſed ſeverall Rebellions, at no time repreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, without great trouble and damage to <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> and without any return of profit to <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> except what by the late habitation of the Engliſh hath been raiſed. And which is moſt remarkable, you ſhall find in all the ſtories of thoſe times. That when thoſe unnaturall Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bels could no longer ſtand out, then who more humble and full of ſubmiſſive flatteries than they, but once taken into mercy: which from time to time they obtained from the indulgent Engliſh (expecting their reducement.) They thereby onely gained breath, and more concur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents to invent and act new wayes of ſupplan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting, ſpoiling, and extirpating thoſe that had the moſt pitty of them. I ſpeak not this that mercy ſhould be denied to whom may be thought worthy of it, yet ſure it is, that if for the multi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plied and itterated Rebellions, and inhuman acts of the Iriſh, the long abuſed Engliſh make a great diſtruction of them, (which God ſeems to dictate in the many ſtrange victories) lately granted by him againſt them. It will come ſhort of <hi>Lex talionis:</hi> yea, it will be nothing ſo much as the Iriſh ever reſolved to execute againſt the true undoubted ancient Proprietors
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:165575:23"/>of that Land, the Engliſh: which may be the more taken to heart, in that it hath been, and is e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vident, that there can be no ſafety in cohabitation with them. And there is none into whoſe hand God puts the ſword of vengeance, that can with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out extream contumacy and diſobedience deny to execute his divine will.</p>
            <p>And now leſt this Proeme ſeem too long, I ſhall lead the worthy Reader, firſt to the particular Heads and Charges againſt theſe Monſters of men, and to the Heads of other Occurrences interlaced, with them and then to the Examinations them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves. Which as is promiſed before (with all poſſible ſpeed) muſt be Printed.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>T. W.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="observations">
            <pb facs="tcp:165575:23"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:165575:24"/>
            <pb n="41" facs="tcp:165575:24"/>
            <head>Obſervations</head>
            <p>
               <hi>To what hath been ſaid in the precedent leaves as concerning matter of fact, and true re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſentation of that incomparable Murther, ſo there is nothing to be added, and it were but impertinencie and provocation to abuſe the Reader with any further instances, and not give him up to his own reſentments and inductions.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>To husband therefore this little room which re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mains, I cannot fall upon a Method either more naturall or regular, then to take a view of the cauſes, concernments and circumſtances, of that odious Conjuration, and from thence deſcend to ſome ſuch obſervations, as cannot (without ſtu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pidity) be paſſed, or impiety, neglected.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">F</seg>Irſt then, whoſoever will take the Iriſh at the right view, will find them a root of ſuch a profound ſloth, and lethargick Supinitie, that they will ſay, they are meerly a kind of <hi>Reptilia,</hi> things creeping on their bellies,
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:165575:25"/>and feeding on the duſt of the earth, overborn with their naturall frigidity, and impoſſible to be excited into any heat, unleſſe it be that fevoriſh diſtemper, which ſometimes ſtirs up the moſt unworthy minds to violent executions. Adde to this, their Innate and Epidemick Laſineſſe which for many ages hath been ſo inherent to them, that they could never be ſtirred, neither by their own neceſſities or diſcomdities of life, to that requiſite induſtry, which even the moſt barbarous, and the beſt ſeated people are forced to make uſe of; Nor yet by the converſation and culture of the more polite Engliſh, could be ſhap't into any adumbration of Civility and terſneſſe, but ſtill re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>main a people ſo exquiſitely ſavage, ſo barba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rouſly lothſom, ſo monſtrouſly enclyn'd, that they were as uncapable of any impreſſions of virtue and honour, as they have ſhewed them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves ſuſceptible of the moſt beſtial lewdneſſe, and conſumate impiety. With theſe qualificati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, they are a people (we may ſuppoſe not ſo fit to bid defiance to a King entirely poſſeſſed with the ſtrength of three kingdoms, and without vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible enemy, although there cannot be denied them ſo much of a punick lightneſſe and raſh prevarica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, as to have ſtaggared into more defections than any people ever yet heard of. Yet were theſe defections but flaſhy tranſportations of weak &amp; abject minds, which having once ſpent their firſt vigor, immediately quit them into their for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer languor, and left thus meerly in a condition
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:165575:25"/>of deſpair and deprecation. Where as this laſt, what by the ſtrength of it's firſt impreſſions, and heat of it's after influences, what by the want of reſiſtance (bloudily deteined from it) hath rather appeared a formall regular War, then a Spartac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ryot, and in ſtead of a ſhort and momentary con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinuance, hath extended it ſelf to the duration of many years; beſides the irremediable Cowardize of that people, never durſt break out into any o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen effort, unleſſe it were backt by ſome ſtrong Forreign aſſurances, or aſſiſtances, or flattered by our diviſions and diverſions, or promoted by their own miſconceived oppreſſions and feigned burthens. But in that poſture of affairs at their Rebellion, there was no ſuch matter, for from <hi>Spain</hi> which (partly out of their own ambition, partly out of that deteſtable zeale to the See of Rome, was commonly wont to lend them fuel to every petulant inſurrection) was not now in a condition to do it. For both the fleet under <hi>Oquen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>do</hi> (which was more than conjecturally ſuppoſed to have been deſigned for <hi>Ireland</hi>) was diſcipated in the <hi>Downs,</hi> and <hi>Spain</hi> her ſelf was at that time ſo beſet, and aſſaulted, that it was viſible to any eye, that ſhe could not afterwards drive any conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derable aſſiſtance to the holy cauſe of Antichriſt, and innocent conventions of Cannibals. And for other nations, the Iriſh were too much diſintereſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed and diſreputed, and we too ſtrong in friends and repute for them to expect thence any valuable advantage.</p>
            <pb n="44" facs="tcp:165575:26"/>
            <p> For the ſecond, we at home were not then one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly of one piece, but were as powerful as we had been for many ages before. Nay, and what was more, we had a Parliament at that time ſitting, ſuch a one as daily ſatisfied the expectations and needs of the people by pious reformations and juſt compliances, ſo that it was not to be thought, but that they who were effectively a whole people, could not be as powerfull in their puniſhments, as they were ſerious and earneſt in their reſent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of ſuch an execrable attempt.</p>
            <p>For the third, they were certainly very peeviſh if they were diſcontented, for they had not onely a Lord Lieuetennant according to their own hearts <hi>(Strafford)</hi> but the ſeverity of the Laws againſt them as diſarmed, or at leaſt a ſleep; they were e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>qually capable of immunities and honours with the Engliſh; And that ſuperſtitious and Antick garb of worſhip was ſo publick, that not onely the ſeverity of the late Lord Chancellour <hi>Loftus,</hi> and the Earl of <hi>Cork</hi> in that matter was eluded, But <hi>Paul Harris,</hi> Sir <hi>Toby Mathews, &amp;c.</hi> (many Sticklers of the See of Room) were in ſight and favour; nay ſome (who have had the beſt reaſon and longeſt time to obſerve it) have affirmed there have been three Maſs Houſes (one at <hi>Naas</hi> a new built ſeat for <hi>Strafford</hi>) open, for one Proteſtant Church.</p>
            <p>All this ſet together, muſt neceſſarily yield us this reſult, that there muſt be ſome more ſecret courſe than ordinary, or ſtranger <hi>Coyuntura</hi> that
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:165575:26"/>quickned the feeds of this horrid Rebellion, and cheriſht it into form and ſhape; for otherwiſe how could it be that thoſe men to whom (though Rebellion) have been ſo naturall and neceſſary, that (not to mention their revolts from their firſt reduction) even in the flouriſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing times of <hi>Queen Eliſabeth,</hi> they nine times for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſook their obedience, could for forty years, fawn upon the Government they ſo much abhor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red; if they could have ſtrengthned their inclinati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons with any hopes or imaginations of ſucceſſe? Certainly he is not skil'd, either in the uſe of things, or nature of the people that thinks they could. But thoſe ſubtile heads that conducted them, ſaw that there was nothing to be attemped, for both our affairs were quiet and ſetled, and the ſeverity of our diſcipline was not utterly loſt; ſo that neither could they with much prudence do any thing of themſelves, or with much aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance attempt the debauching of men in authority, who did not then appear ſuch abſolutely profeſſed Huckſters and Brokers of their Country, as they might be hoped to be wone to parly, All that that viperous generation could do, (and theſe were the Jeſuites, or Jeſuited) was with all their diligence and Artifice, to poſſeſſe theſe people with a blind and ſottiſh preoccupation, and then to caſt ſuch wild fire into their paſſions, that they might be directed to nothing which they ſhould not preſently act, nor act any thing wherein they might not ſhew ſuch brutiſh and inſatiate cruelty,
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:165575:27"/>as might over revenge the greateſt Iujuries, ſecure the greateſt Cowardize, and glut the vileſt Inhu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manity.</p>
            <p>And how effectual all this proviſion was, and how fit Mirmidons they had to inſtruct, was ſeen in thoſe fatall butcheries which fill the other Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges: For whether theſe unnatural monſters (or rather Fiends informing humane carkaſes) were not in all numbers perfected in cruelty, perfidy, and licentious impiety. He hath little reaſon, ſence or obſervation, that cannot judge.</p>
            <p>Yet durſt not they (as he ſaid) have put this into action, (though they earneſtly waited and thirſted after it) had they not found the Court of <hi>England</hi> in a condition to be tampered with, and the ſame Court alſo (loaded with its iniqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, and boading eminent vengeance) willing to ſtrike a league with any that might underprop them; and from hence (no doubt) began this e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vill to take both root and life, and its Mercurial Projectors to put it in agitation; which wrought ſo throughly upon a Popiſh gangren'd Court, and an Uxorious perverſe King, that it brake forth with that ſtorm and impetuoſity, that (had not God mightily owned his own cauſe) it was likely to have ſhaked the foundation of three Nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons.</p>
            <p>For why ſhould the naked and raw Iriſh (that had neither preparation for War nor intelligence) ruſh on a deſign which the moſt powerful Prince in Europe would hardly have embarqued in? how
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:165575:27"/>could all have been ſo generally engaged, even to them of the Palle, without ſome ſtrong allure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments or fair Commiſſions? What ſignified thoſe mid-night debates of <hi>Muskery</hi> and <hi>Plunket</hi> (Principal Actors after,) with the King, to the amazement and dejection of that honeſt remnant at Court? How came theſe bloudy wretches ſuch Patrons of the Kings cauſe? and though they abo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minated his pretended Religion, to agree with him in <hi>eodem tertio</hi> againſt the Parliament? For it ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pears by <hi>Mervin Stewards</hi> 8. c. Depoſitions, that the Perogative was a main ground of their Rebellion. Nay their intereſt and greateſt ſecurity was involved in it. Nor wanted there on the Kings ſide either reaſons of intereſt, or (it may be) great deſign: for by the deſtruction of the Proteſtants, the Iriſh were intire, and at leaſure for his ſervice, and ſo might be aſſiſtant to him againſt the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vailing Puritan faction (as he called it) in his two other Realms; Or (to put the moſt moderate gloſſe upon ſo fowl an action) he did ſuppoſe that that eruption would onely have ſtruck a ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ror, and have been ſoon appeaſed, and not have brought with it ſuch a violent and continual ſtorm of miſchiefs. Or was it a ſerious deſire to divert the Parliament, from theſe proſecuti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of liberty, to which he perceived them earn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſtly to encline. Howſoever, certainly he that will but diligently examine Circumſtances, muſt needs find him tranſcendently guilty, (for it is no cruelty to the dead, to examine thoſe actions<gap reason="illegible: missing" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="48" facs="tcp:165575:28"/>God hath ſo ſeverely puniſhed and avenged) for if we find him the Author of the Rebellion, (as we ſhall bring ſome ſhrewd inſtances) we muſt needs affirm, that though his Theatricall piety and high diſſimulation, hath deceived ſome of his followers into Adoration, yet to all men that have not a miſt before their eyes, he will appear a perſon diſtained with ſo much bloud, and loaden with ſo many crimes, that he was equal to all paſt Ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rants in his iniquities, as he will be exemplary to all future by his puniſhment. Or if we find him but an aſſiſter or a complier, (for this is the leaſt we can do, yet leſſe than we ought) let even his own Devines who could ſo dextrouſly Incruſtate and opiate his conſcience, themſelves be Judges, whether his concurrence with ſuch ſavage fiends, his eaſie forgiveneſſe of ſo much bloud, his com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pliance with Idolatry, and that againſt ſo many ſolemn vows and imprecations, were not many provocations of the Divine vengeance, which ſo tranſcendently and exemplarily fell upon him.</p>
            <p>To clear up this I know not any better way than by repreſenting his actions, (and that without either exageration, or impoſture) and carriages about the time and after that fatall violence, which it ſeems wrought ſo little upon him, that many actors in it were ſhortly ſeen with him, and his own Ceſſati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on with the Iriſh declares, he knew how to for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>get it, and make it to contribute to his own cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupt ends, which will appear the more manifeſt,
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:165575:28"/>if we take but the pains to look over thoſe par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticulars, which even in the middeſt of their com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plementing (to ſay ſo) times, the Parliament did not ſtick to object againſt him, with as great aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance, as he declined to anſwer them with difi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence, or (to ſpeake in the words of ſervil flatte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry it ſelf) prudent diſſimulation, for whoſoever (to remarke it by the way) ſhall obſerve all his Declarations, or that venemous fraudulent <hi>Pamph<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>let</hi> under his name, he muſt needs ſee how unwil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and tender he is, when he comes to touch on this ſtring; but inſtead of bringing any probable ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guments to avoid it, he Lancheth out whole vol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lies of daring curſes upon himſelf and his, or elſe fals upon contrary recriminations of the Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament, that <q>The Iriſh might alledge them for imitation, whoſe blame muſt be the greater,<note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>. Chap. 12.</note> by how much Proteſtant Principles, are more againſt Rebellion than Papiſts.</q> Three lyes impudently ſtufft together.</p>
            <p>Firſt, that the Parliament gave example to the Rebels. Next, that they are more to blame. Third<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, that Proteſtantiſme puts people into an inca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pacity to right themſelves, or calling to acount. (This he means by the word <hi>Rebellions,</hi> Tyrants!) Will you have any more? for never were falſities ſo cloſely and nicely couched, as in that deceitfull Peace,) <q>Many wiſe men thought that prepoſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous rigour and unreaſonable ſeverity, blew up thoſe ſparks of diſcontent.</q> How diveliſhly is the pious care of Religion in the Parliament made a
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:165575:29"/>cauſe of ſo much bloud and miſe ries? But hark what he hath to ſay for the Rebels. <q>Fear of utter exterpation, continuance of oppreſſion, ſome Principles of their Religion, Naturall deſire of liberty, made them endeavour to exempt them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves from after rigour, threatned by the cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tous zeal and uncharitable fury of ſome men.</q> See how Satyricall he is on the one ſide, whilſt for the other he brings arguments ſo paſſionate and emphaticall, as the greateſt Advocate might make uſe of. Nor ſee I (indeed) how ſtronger can be brought, then thoſe he falſly brings in this place, which he makes uſe of for the Iriſh to go on; he ſais <q>Next to the ſin of thoſe, is theirs, who hindered the ſpeedy ſuppreſſing of it by Domeſtick diſentions, diverting aids.</q> (which we ſhall prove he did,) Onely you may know whom they would have us mean, <q>and exaſpera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted the Rebels to deſperate reſolutions, by threat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning extremity on their heads!</q> Obdurate man given up to thine own blindneſſe and hardneſſe of heart, thou couldſt not have ſaid any thing fuller of Atheiſticall ſpleen, or uncharitable looſneſs. Thoſe men muſt march on the left-hand of ſuch Divels, for profeſſing their zeal and upright<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe to the cauſe of God, which to have hand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led luke-warmly, had been ſin of a crying na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture; to have deſerted, had been to ſhare in the vengeance of thoſe wicked wretches, and to have brought on their own heads that ſhame ard ven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geance which for the cauſe fell on them. Theſe are
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:165575:29"/>his lateſt and dying reflections of that buſineſſe which we ſhall now return into, from the neceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry digreſſions.</p>
            <p>Thus there was a prediſpoſition in the Court of <hi>England</hi> for ſuch deſigns as theſe; we ſhall need onely to remember that in the ſecond year of his reign, (To indulge Popery, <hi>by Chriſtning, Marrying, Suſpending</hi> proceedings againſt Papiſts, To alow ſueing out Liveries and Ouſterlemains by the Papiſts, without taking the oath of Alle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giance. This deſign which (for a ſum of money was to bring in further tolleration of Religion) was proteſted againſt by the Iriſh Biſhops, by writing under their hands of the 26. of <hi>No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vember</hi> 1626. and the Commons of <hi>England</hi> in their Remonſtrance the thrird of <hi>Carolus,</hi> did in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form that Popery was profeſſed, and Monaſtries repleniſhed every where, deſiring him to take the advice of themſelvs and Biſhops into conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deration. Yet,</p>
            <p>In the fourth year of his Reign, thoſe Propo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitions and Graces with additions did he grant in conſideration of one hundred and twenty thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand pounds, to be levied upon the Kingdom in generall, ſo that the poor Proteſtants were il<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>legally oppreſſed to gain the Papiſts Immuni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties.</p>
            <p>Many notorious Papiſts were created Peers, whereby the Popiſh votes in the Lords houſe en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſed, and the Papiſts became more powerfull and exemplary in their Counties.</p>
            <pb n="52" facs="tcp:165575:30"/>
            <p> When the Lord Chancellour <hi>Loftus,</hi> and the Earl of <hi>Cork</hi> were Lords-Juſtices; and endeavoured to put down Maſs-houſes; and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt the reſt, converted one (in <hi>Backlane</hi> in <hi>Dublin</hi>) to a Colledge, where Lectures were read, (which the Lords-Juſtices did to the encou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ragement of Proteſtants) yet when <hi>Strafford</hi> came, the Schollars were diſplaced, and it became a Maſs-houſe again.</p>
            <p>The Popiſh Iriſh Army was kept on foot long after the beginning of the Parliament, and contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry to their deſires, whereby thoſe execrable vil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lains learned the knowledge of Arms, under the pretence of fighting againſt <hi>Scotland.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And that Lead might not be wanting to the compleating of this intended Rebellion, (I uſe the very words of that excellent Declaration of the 25. of <hi>July</hi> 1643.) as it had been in the laſt great Rebellion there, the Silver-mynes of that Kingdom (which afforded great ſtore of Lead) were farmed out by his Majeſty, to two (moſt pernitious) Papiſts, Sir <hi>Bazill Brooke,</hi> and Sir <hi>George Hamilton;</hi> In whoſe houſes (upon ſearch) divers barrels of Muſquet-bullets were found.</p>
            <p>Before the Rebellion <hi>Strafford</hi> had (by violent endeavour) entituled his Majeſty by office, to five whole Counties, and a great part of two o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, whereby a way was made to increaſe Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, Plantations and Safetie: Which the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mittee (ſent over for complaint of Grievances) did never complain of, (as conceiving it diſtaſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full)
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:165575:30"/>yet when the King had offered to reſtore it to the Proprietors, and the Lords-Juſtices impor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuned him to the contrary, and the then Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment had diſcovered much of the Iriſh Counſels, then (ſubtilties no longer ſerving them) was new projected and allowed this hideous Rebellion, (that after fell out) by <hi>Gormondſton, Muskery, Plunket, Linch</hi> and <hi>Browne,</hi> who were conſulted with, and carraſed at <hi>Whitehall,</hi> had private con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference with the King in the Queens preſence; And what agreement was made may eaſily be imagi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, (for witneſſes are not to be expected at a conſpiracy, of ſuch importance) by the Kings giving away five whole Counties (after ſo great an endeavour of many years to entitle him to them, accounting it a Maſter-piece of <hi>Strafford</hi>) and that for the yearly rent of two thouſand pounds. When in ſearching Records, and mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuring the land it had coſt the King more than ten thouſand pounds out of his Coffers.</p>
            <p>Let any compare the <hi>Iudulgence</hi> with the <hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>juſtice</hi> to the <hi>Londoners</hi> in <hi>Derry</hi> and <hi>Colrain,</hi> (which ſhews land in <hi>Ireland</hi> worth owning) when there is no recompence for parting with it: For the King told the Committee of <hi>Ireland,</hi> That ſince he had parted with ſo much of his right, he muſt be recompenced ſome other way: And he would ſoon infer that ſo large a Donative (eſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally conſidering the bountiful nature of that King) was not ſown upon the ſand.</p>
            <pb n="54" facs="tcp:165575:31"/>
            <p> And that theſe blades might not be awanting in the requitall of ſo conſiderable a favour, they re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turned into <hi>Ireland,</hi> in <hi>Auguſt</hi> after, where how that they beſtirred themſelves may appear: For in the three and twentieth of <hi>October</hi> following, the Rebelion brake forth in <hi>Vlſter.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>To theſe violent preſumptions, muſt be added the concurrence of the Engliſh Papiſts, to this buſineſſe, as is copiouſly proved by the Depoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions forementioned, and the repair of <hi>Caſtleha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, Young, Porter, Endimions own ſonne,</hi> Sir <hi>Bazill Brooke</hi> and <hi>Browne</hi> the Lawyer into <hi>Ireland,</hi> where they were main ſticklers in that hainous Rebel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lion.</p>
            <p>Nay in that moneth of <hi>October</hi> (fatall for that deluge of bloud) the Lord <hi>Dillon Costiloghe</hi> (an Iriſh Rebel) went from <hi>Scotland</hi> from the King, into <hi>Ireland</hi> with his Majeſties letters, (by the Queens means) to be ſworn Privie Councellor, which was no ſooner done, but he preſents to the Lords Juſtices &amp; Councel an inſolent letter of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monſtrance, of ſome inhabitants of the County of <hi>Longford,</hi> wherein they unreaſonably demand Tol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leration, repealing of Laws <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Nay, &amp; this Lord might by his motion teſtifie that he was alive: For in the following <hi>December,</hi> he with the new Lord <hi>Taaff,</hi> came into <hi>England</hi> with inſtructions in writing from <hi>Gormonſton</hi> and others, to ſolicite with his Majeſty in their behalf, which (it ſeems they did ſo effectually, that they in his Majeſties name encouraged the Rebels, as may appear by a
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:165575:31"/>ſignal Depoſition of Col. <hi>Iepſon.</hi> Who ſaw two Letters of theirs ſent to <hi>Muskery,</hi> intimating, That though it did not ſtand with the conveniency of his Majeſties affairs to give him publick countenance, yet his Majeſty was pleaſed with what he did; and would in good time give him thanks for it.</p>
            <p>This though diſcovered to the Lord <hi>Falkland</hi> then Secretary, and though Colonel <hi>Iepſon</hi> ſtayed a week after in <hi>Oxford,</hi> was ſo coldly entertained, that neither the Colonel was called to account, nor the Lords leſſened of their freedom and fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour.</p>
            <p>Nay the ſaid <hi>Taaff,</hi> was afterwards imployed with <hi>Roch</hi> and <hi>Brent</hi> (two active Papiſts) taking with them Colonel <hi>Barry</hi> one of the ſame fry, to carry the Kings letters from <hi>Oxford</hi> to <hi>Dublin.</hi> From whence they made away for <hi>Kilkeny,</hi> where there was to be (ſoon after) a generall aſſembly of the Rebels: which Errand when they had perfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med, <hi>Barry</hi> was left Leaguer at <hi>Kilkenny, Taaff,</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turned to <hi>Dublin.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Taaff</hi> with divers of diſaffected Privy-Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellours of <hi>Ireland,</hi> meets at <hi>Ormonds</hi> houſe, to debate the Iriſh Propoſitions, and <hi>Brent</hi> returns to <hi>Oxford</hi> to give an account of the Negotiati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. By this we may the better conceive what the King meant by that deluſory offer to go into <hi>Ire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land.</hi> Whether it were under this plauſible pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence to get a Guard about him, and by that degree a conſiderable force, or when he was once there either to make a Ceſſation advantageous to him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf,
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:165575:32"/>or elſe to joyn with them; however, it was a pretence good enough to decline Signings and Confeſſions, (advantagious to his ſubjects in <hi>England</hi>) and increaſe Jealouſies at home, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tard the buſineſſe of the Parliament (then in full heat and action) whatever it were: Certain it is, that there lurkt within it ſomewhat of deep deſign, and very exquiſite miſchief; For, even the very Rebels could without Proſpective ſee it, and without a Divel foretell it. For, <hi>Tirlogh ô Neal</hi> could (as appears by Maſter <hi>Stewarts</hi> examination, taken the eighth day of <hi>July</hi> 1643.) tell, that the King was to be ſoon in <hi>Ireland,</hi> and Sir <hi>Phelim ô Neal</hi> could give out, that the troubles of <hi>England</hi> would ere long call away <hi>Leiſley</hi> to aſſiſt them. Nor is it any wonder that theſe people were ſo perfect in the Kings deſigns, and ſo fore-ſeeing of our troubles, when they were part both of the intereſt and Plot, that in deed (if you will take their own words) the Kings cauſe and theirs, were fundamentally and really one, though pollitically and ſpetiouſly devided. How elſe ſhould <hi>Tirlogh ô Neal,</hi> and <hi>Roger ô Moore</hi> (as is in Maſter <hi>Stewarts</hi> mentioned Depoſition) ſay, <hi>That Religion, the Lands eſchea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, and the Kings Prerogative, were the prime cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes of their riſing in Arms? That they knew well the best in</hi> England <hi>would ſide with them? That they had good warrant in black and white for what they did? That when he objected the Power of</hi> Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land <hi>would he brought against them, they replied,
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:165575:32"/>That there was little feare of that, for the troubles in</hi> England <hi>were but then in beginning, and would not end in haſte.</hi> And how elſe could <hi>Rory Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guyre</hi> ſay, <hi>That they</hi> (the Parliament) <hi>invaded the Kings Prerogative, in which their greateſt ſecurity repoſed? That this great undertaking, was never an act of one or two giddy ſilly fellowes? They had their party in</hi> England, Scotland, &amp;c. <hi>which ſhould ſoon be as deep in bloud as themſelves? That the Plot had been of ancient date, and many times diſcontinued, and but lately revived, and proſecuted from Candelmas laſt past.</hi> (Note the time of <hi>Gor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manſton</hi> and the reſt procuring the five Counties) <hi>before the Rebellion both in</hi> England <hi>and</hi> Scotland. All is depoſed by that Apoſtate <hi>Awdley Mervin,</hi> (whoſe ſiſter, <hi>Maguire</hi> married) <hi>who heard it from many more</hi> (as himſelf depoſeth) <hi>of conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derable quality;</hi> Nay, <hi>Why did they of the</hi> Palle <hi>de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare, to joyn with the Iriſh to recover to his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty his Royall Prerogative, wrung from him by the Puritan faction,</hi> Why was the Deſign called <hi>the Queens pious intentions?</hi>
               <note place="margin">Decl. 9. <hi>March</hi> 1641.</note> Why did <hi>Roſſetti</hi> (the Popes Nuncio) <hi>enjoyn Faſting and Prayer amongſt the Papiſts? Why were the Proteſtants called Rebells to the Queen? How came the Rebells to aſsume the Kings Authority,</hi> Nay boldly aver <hi>they had his Commiſſion:</hi> Inſomuch that the Major of <hi>Kinſale</hi> writes, <hi>That they uttered things concerning the Court of</hi> Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land, <hi>which he durſt not put to Paper.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And now let any man lay his hand upon his heart, and ſay whether or no he can acquit this
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:165575:33"/>man of theſe things. Certainly ignorance in this caſe could not be pretended even to people that had but the bare uſe of common ſence; and to be paſſive in a buſineſſe of this nature, muſt needs be a ſin not much leſſe than violent action: But to give en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couragement and groth to ſuch abominable Mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters (as from what has been layd down, muſt needs be clear to every diſpaſſioned Judgment, eſpecially ſince ſuch uncontrolable preſumption may ſerve in the works of darkneſſe) is ſuch an offence, that it muſt needs lead any ſober and ſearching mind in a clear trace of the Divine vengeance upon it. God indeed is ſecret &amp; marvel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous in executing his wrath, and many times openly puniſheth unknown crimes, and many times diſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles the ſeeing of crying offences: But in this caſe, both the one and the other were equally viſible, and we may without uncharitableneſſe, affirm, That for theſe things was this man rooted out of the Land.</p>
            <p>We have now viewed him on the Divels-ſide of the Meddal, let us now behold him on the Saint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſide, and find out one of the moſt illuſtrous diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſimulations that ever atteſted Piety: a diſſimula<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion which a Heathen, under the crepuſculous daies of nature, would have ſtarted back at; and have immagined it, either beyond puniſhment, or els meriting Judgments and Torments ſeverer than any he knew. A diſſimulation by a Proteſtant King in behalf of Traiterous Papiſts, and that to lull and ſtupifie his own ſubjects, (and of his
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:165575:33"/>own Religion) into bloud and deſtruction.</p>
            <p>The minds of men were not yet ſo exquiſitely debauched, but they were open to the ſerious ma<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nifeſtation of their Repreſentatives, nor the Kings buſineſſe in ſuch a poſture, that he might declare and juſtifie his proceedings, nor his Innocencie ſuch, as he might vindicate himſelf. And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore to theſe Remonſtrative objections of the Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament, he had nothing to ſay; but ſuch whole peals of ſolemn and dire imprecations, as if he thought Perjury lawfull and eſſentiall to his cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling: Or elſe Divinity to be a meer <hi>Mormo</hi> and ſtaring <hi>Rodomontade.</hi> Or elſe he had utterly forgot what he had deſigned ſome moneths before; or were aſleep to all his preſent actions or carri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ages; or had been informed with a new ſoul, when he had acted thoſe things which he did after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards.</p>
            <p>For inſtances, they throng upon us (Reader pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pare thy horror) in his ſpeech to the Committee at <hi>Newark</hi> the ninth of <hi>March</hi> 1641. <hi>God will diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver the ſecret of Plots and Treaſons. He ſhall ſtand right in the eyes of his people. My fears are greater for the Proteſtant Relegion than for my own Rights or ſafety. God ſo deal with me and mine, as all my thoughts are upright for the maintenance of the Proteſtant Religion and Laws, &amp;c.</hi> Thus in his Meſſage of the eighth of <hi>April</hi> 1642. <hi>He aſſures them, he will never, upon any pretence whatſoever, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent to a tolleration of the Popiſh Religion in</hi> Ireland, <hi>or abolition of the Laws in force against the Papiſts,</hi>
               <pb n="60" facs="tcp:165575:34"/>which how ſtrictly he kept, look in <hi>Ormonds Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cification</hi> 1648. Where you may ſee, the firſt Article quits them of the oath of Supreamicy; The ſecond puts into the hand of an Iriſh Parliament, to repeal <hi>Poinings</hi> Act. The 22. (O ridiculous in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dulgence and ſervill compliances) repeals thoſe Acts prohibiting to plow with horſes by the tail, and burn Oats in the ſtraw. The ninth entruſteth them with the Militia, which the King ſwore, or (in the Parliaments language) ſtrongly aſſevered by God, at <hi>Newmarket,</hi> he would not truſt the Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament with, for an hour; and grants, till the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formance, an Army of 20000 men. All which put together ſignifies the alienation of all <hi>Ireland.</hi> Or will you hear him when he was about to die? (for certainly any man that conſiders the choiſe of the ſubjects of the <hi>Black-book</hi> cleanly, cannot but acknowledge he writ it in his later time, on purpoſe to abuſe the people into credulity and fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour of his actions, and ſo poyſon them after his death.) <hi>If I have deſired or delighted in the wofull day of my Kingdoms Calamities</hi> (and yet he was the cauſe.) <hi>If I have not earneſtly ſtudied the preventing of thoſe bloudy diſtractions, then let thy hand be upon me and my Fathers houſe,</hi> &amp;c. Which, to the great praiſe of the Divine Juſtice, we ſee accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pliſht.</p>
            <p>You ſee how he hath dared the omniſcient ear of Providence, and you have ſeen with what event, and no doubt among mankind (at leaſt the better and reſonable part) his name will alſo ſtink when
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:165575:34"/>they are throughly convinced of his odious and unkingly Diſſimulation; Which beſides its own unworthyneſſe, muſt needs adde a great weight to the preſumptions of his guilt.</p>
            <p>Theſe deteſtable Cyclops, had at firſt from him, their due attributes. There was no expreſſions too tart or indignatory for them. In his anſwer to the <hi>Declaration Auguſt</hi> 1642. he calls it <hi>a bloudy Maſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſacre.</hi> In his ſpeech to them of <hi>Denbigh</hi> and <hi>Flint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhire</hi> 1643. he calls it, <hi>an horrid bloudy and impi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Rebellion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In his anſwer to the Petition of the 8 of <hi>April</hi> 1042. he calls the Iriſh, <hi>Barbarous Rebels, authors of great calamities and unheard of cruelties, to his Protestant ſubjects.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In his meſſage of the eighth of <hi>April</hi> 1642. He calls them, <hi>Wicked and detestable Rebels, odious to God and all good men.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And yet notwiſtanding all theſe ſmart and home expreſſions and manifeſtations, (and his zealous ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lerity in proſecuting <hi>Scotland</hi>) it was long ere (up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on deſire of both houſes) he could be perſwaded to proclaim them Rebels, (notwithſtanding they called themſelves the Queens Army) and at laſt three moneths after, he would ſuffer but forty to be printed, and thoſe warily diſperſed. Yet was this but a faint courteſie to what he did for them other wiſe, all deſigns of the Parliament for their pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhment were obviated by him and fruſtrated; all ſuccours ſent, averted or deteined to maintain an unnaturall War againſt his Porteſtant Subjects.</p>
            <pb n="62" facs="tcp:165575:35"/>
            <p> Take a few inſtances, (we could be copious were plenty neceſſary) he would not grant a Committee to be ſent into <hi>Ireland,</hi> he deterred the Officers of <hi>Lemster</hi> from new ſubſcription (which he thought was a probable way to reducethat Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vince without charges,) then in motion in Parl. Nay when ſome well-affected had prepared twelve ſhips and ſix pinnaces, he would grant no Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion til they were forced to go by Ordinance of Parliament. When the Lords Juſtices of <hi>Ireland</hi> ſent for two pieces of Battery, he by expreſſe command hindred any to be delivered out of the Tower. <hi>Floid</hi> and <hi>Green,</hi> he recalled from the I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſh ſervice. <hi>Stradling</hi> and <hi>Kettlesby,</hi> he called away from the Iriſh Coaſts, when they lay there on purpoſe to prevent the carrying in of Ammuni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. Nay, much proviſion deſigned thither, by his forces he plundered, and many of the Parliaments ſhips, by his letters of Mart, were ſeized on; as may largely appear in the Collection of Declarations <hi>p.</hi> 250. <hi>&amp; ſubſequentibus.</hi> To ad to all this, his fraudu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent delaying &amp; dallying of the Earl of <hi>Leceſter,</hi> as may appear by the Earls own letter, of the 26. of <hi>Sept.</hi> 1642: yea when the Iriſh were almoſt ſtarved (though loaden with ſo much guilt and bloud) yet could they procure a Commiſſion to examine their grievances; and at laſt had a Ceſſation granted them, which the King (for ſooth) ſaith, was to ſave the remainder of his Proteſtant ſubjects.</p>
            <p>And now Reader, ſtand ſtill and ſee the moſt no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>torious perſidie both in a King and his Rebels (or
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:165575:35"/>to ſay better) his Confederates that ever was, how God hath puniſhed the one, is as viſible as a Sun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beam, ſince he (as he made up the iniquities, ſo he) hath found the Tragical Cataſtrophe (yet by lawfull and juſt means and pleaſing to God) of his predeceſſors, and remains a terrour and example to all that ſhall come after him: And for them, he is blind that ſeeth them not at the brink of the pit, and he is accurſed that ſhall offer to ſtay them: and therefore let them into whoſe hands God hath put the ſword of his wrath, take heed leſt they uſe it either coldly, partially, or negligently; leſt God ſmite them, and raiſe up others to execute his juſt vengeance. And what a ſinne it will be to be even moderate in a work ſo pleaſing to God, let their own conſciences be Judges. God will not be dallied with, he hateth ſhedding of inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent bloud. Breach of Oaths and Rebellion, which were never more ſublime and horrid than in thoſe people, whom certainly he is reſolved to blow as chaffe from the face of the earth. And therefore cannot but ſeverely puniſh any luke warmneſſe (for mercy to them is no other) in his inſtruments.</p>
            <p>And indeed it is obſervable, that as God hath migh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tily puniſhed thoſe ſinful concurrences of the King, and wicked Ceſſations and compliances of <hi>Ormond</hi> &amp; his Complices, ſo hath he led our army, as it were by the hand, in giving them <hi>Tredarth,</hi> and his almoſt mediate interpoſitions of Articles of Surrender at <hi>Wexford.</hi> And after thoſe two juſt and acceptable ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ecutions, hath more vigorouſly protected and gone
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:165575:36"/>along with them. The hearts of their enemies being filled with trembling, and the gates of the City, in a manner, thrown down before them.</p>
            <p>Nor indeed is there any policy (were the other confederations nothing) to ſtrik a league with ſuch unfaithfull, wretched, cruel, ſavage, accurſed peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple as they are, unleſſe we ſhould be cumbered with a deſpicable crue of wretches, and neglect one of the braveſt pieces of Juſtice that ever was put into the hands of people. And therefore, we may warantably, and righteouſly endeavour the extir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pation of them, who by their helliſh deſigns, and accompliſht Parricides, have endeavoured, and highly attempted, to make us to be <hi>no more a peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple.</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
